{"tossups": [{"question": "As a state representative, this man sponsored the anti-contraception law that was overturned a century later in<em> Griswold v. Connecticut</em>. This man built two mansions in Bridgeport and patronized the U.S. tour of the \u201cSwedish Nightingale,\u201d opera singer Jenny Lind. This business partner of James Bailey died three decades before his company was merged with that of the Ringling Brothers. For the point, name this 19th century entrepreneur whose \u201cGreatest Show on Earth\u201d became America\u2019s largest circus.", "answer": "Phineas Taylor \u201cP.T.\u201d<b> Barnum</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Troops were parachuted into this battle during Operation Castor. The outposts Beatrice and Gabrielle were captured during this battle, in which Charles Piroth committed suicide by hand grenade after failing to destroy the camouflaged artillery of Vo Nguyen Giap. This battle led to the signing of the Geneva Accords, in which one side agreed to withdraw from Indochina. For the point, name this 1953 victory for the Viet Minh in their struggle for independence from France.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Dien Bien Phu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Fighting in this war included the shelling of dockyards at Sveaborg. This conflict escalated when one side claimed the right to protect holy places in Palestine, and its immediate cause was the destruction of an Ottoman fleet in the Battle of Sinope [sin-oh-pee]. The Thin Red Line participated in the Battle of Balaclava, part of the effort to besiege Sevastopol during this war. The Light Brigade charged in, for the point, what 1850s war between Russia and a Franco-British alliance on a Black Sea peninsula?", "answer": "<b> Crimean</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For his failure to warn the United States about this event, Michael Fortier was sentenced to twelve years in prison in 1998. One perpetrator of this action used the alias \u201cRobert D. Kling\u201d to obtain a rental truck. Terry Nichols was an accomplice in this crime, which was inspired by the Ruby Ridge and Waco sieges. The deadliest pre-9/11 terrorist attack in American history was, for the point, what April 1995 attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building by Timothy McVeigh?", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma City</b> bombing (or<b> OKC</b> bombing; accept equivalents for bombing, like \u201cattack\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A poem by this author compares \u201cAs my soul in its trouble dissatisfied sank\u201d to a \u201cwestern orb sailing the heaven\u201d that drops into the night. This man imagined a swaying mass with \u201ceager faces turning\u201d in a poem in which the \u201cprize we sought is won\u201d and \u201cour fearful trip is done.\u201d This author wrote \u201cWhen Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom\u2019d\u201d and \u201cO Captain! My Captain!\u201d as elegies for Abraham Lincoln. For the point, name this American poet whose works were collected in his poetry collection<em> Leaves of Grass</em>.", "answer": "Walt<b> Whitman</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "Suetonius claims that this man was the first to begin construction of a canal across the Isthmus of Corinth. This man put down the Pisonian Conspiracy, which involved his tutor, Seneca the Younger. The Revolt of Boudica and the First Jewish Revolt occurred during this man\u2019s rule. The death of this last member of the Julio-Claudian Dynasty led to the Year of the Four Emperors. For the point, name this Roman Emperor who legendarily fiddled as Rome burned.", "answer": "<b> Nero</b> Cladius Caesar Augustus Germanicus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, troops under Thomas Mullins failed to breach enemy lines after forgetting to bring along ladders. For aiding the winning side in this battle, the pirate Jean Lafitte earned a federal pardon. Edward Pakenham died during this battle, which occurred a few weeks after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent, \u201cending\u201d its war. Only eight Americans died in, for the point, what final battle in the War of 1812 that bolstered the reputation of Andrew Jackson?", "answer": "Battle of<b> New Orleans</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Administration within this country was divided along the Leitha River as part of the Compromise of 1867, which sought to restore stability after its defeat by Prussia. The Treaty of Trianon helped dissolve this country, which was formed by the Ausgleich. Its rulers were described as \u201cImperial and Royal,\u201demphasizing their pair of titles in this Dual Monarchy. For the point, name this country, ruled jointly from Budapest and Vienna until it dissolved after World War I.", "answer": "<b> Austria-Hungary</b> (prompt on Dual Monarchy until mention; do not accept or prompt on Austria or Hungary alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this war, Congressman Joe Martin read a letter stating \u201cthere is no substitute for victory.\u201dNear the end of this war, a series of battles during a stalemate included the Battles of the Punchbowl and Pork Chop Hill. This war\u2019s MiG Alley was contested by numerous jet fighters, and during this war, the popular Douglas MacArthur was relieved of command by President Truman. The U.S. led the UN Command in, for the point, what 1950 to 1953 war fought on an Asian peninsula?", "answer": "<b> Korean</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The non-fiction book<em> The Courtier and the Heretic</em> was written about this man\u2019s discussions with Leibniz over his most famous work, which describes the universe as comprised of God\u2019s \u201cmodes.\u201d This philosopher promoted the principle of \u201cpantheism,\u201d claiming that God and the universe were synonymous and interchangeable. This man was banished from the Jewish community of Amsterdam for his heretical beliefs. For the point, name this Dutch 17th-century philosopher and author of<em> Ethics</em>.", "answer": "Baruch<b> Spinoza</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "For the point, name this Asian archipelagic nation once led by Sukarno from Jakarta.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Indonesia</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A Scottish invasion of this monarch\u2019s land was repulsed by the Earl of Surrey, leading to the death of James IV. This propagator of the first Act of Supremacy faced a rebellion from Robert Aske known as the Pilgrimage of Grace during his dissolution of the monasteries. Cardinal Wolsey, Thomas Cromwell, and Thomas Cranmer were all advisers of this king, who broke with the Catholic Church to form the Church of England. For the point, name this Tudor monarch of England who was married six times.", "answer": "<b> Henry VIII</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A recent performance of this opera in New York was cut short by the police after a man dumped his mentor\u2019s ashes in the orchestra pit. In this opera, the princess Mathilde sings \u201cSombre foret\u201d while at Rutli. Its antagonist was the 13th-century Hapsburg governor of Uri and Schwyz, Albrecht Gessler. A\u201ccall to the cows\u201d and the galop \u201cMarch of the Swiss Soldiers\u201d are featured in the famous overture to, for the point, what Rossini opera about a Swiss folk hero who shot an apple off his son\u2019s head?", "answer": "<b> William Tell</b> (or<b> Guillaume Tell</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this event, Herman Husband was arrested by a \u201cWatermelon Army,\u201d despite his moderate voice at a convention in modern-day Monongahela. During this event, Bower Hill, the home of General John Neville, was burned to the ground. A Congressman charged that Alexander Hamilton deliberately provoked this violent event, which was suppressed by an army led by George Washington himself. For the point, name this 1790\u2019s uprising in western Pennsylvania that was directed against a tax on alcohol.", "answer": "<b> Whiskey</b> Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "John Sheehan was the first scientist to perform a chemical synthesis of this compound after Dorothy Hodgkin determined its structure. This compound, which has a beta-lactam ring at its center, inhibits the cross-linking synthesis of cell walls in bacteria. Its discover shared the Nobel Prize with Florey and Chain for their work on mass producing this compound during World War II. For the point, name this antibiotic discovered in mold in 1928 by Alexander Fleming.", "answer": "<b> penicillin</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "The Fountain of the Eagle is located in this country, whose railway opened in 1933 with one station. A landmark in this country contains an obelisk first transported from Egypt under the reign of Caligula. It was recognized in 1929 by the Lateran Treaty, which ended a fifty-nine year period of its leader being a \u201cprisoner\u201d here following the Risorgimento. Saint Peter\u2019s Square is located in, for the point, what tiny independent country within the borders of Rome, ruled by the Pope?", "answer": "<b> Vatican</b> City (or the<b> Vatican</b>; do not accept or prompt on Italy) Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The necessity of these institutions was questioned by the Ringle Report. Victims of these locations were compensated $20,000 when Ronald Reagan signed the Civil Liberties Act into law. These locations were judged to be constitutional in<em> Korematsu v United States</em>, which ruled that the security interests of the United States outweighed the individual rights of the plaintiff. Manzanar was an example of, for the point, what World War II-era locations in which members of a certain Asian ethnicity were forced to live?", "answer": "Japanese(-American)<b> internment </b> <b>camp</b>s (accept<b> Japanese</b>-American<b> concentration camp</b>s; prompt on concentration camps; prompt on partial answers, like \u201ccamps for Japanese(-Americans)\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was the target of an attempted coup by the H\u00b4ebertists. With his ally, Georges Danton, this man led the Montagnards. This man established the Cult of the Supreme Being to oppose the Cult of Reason and reverse the process of de-Christianization. This member of the Committee of Public Safety was executed after the Thermidorian Reaction. For the point, name this Jacobin that masterminded the Reign of Terror during the French Revolution and got rid of numerous opponents with his guillotine.", "answer": "Maximilien<b> Robespierre</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The lowest portion of this body of water is Sigsbee Deep. A portion of this body of water, the Bay of Campeche [cam-pay-chay], was home to the Ixtoc I [ish-tok one] blowout. This body of water contains the Macondo Prospect, where an oil rig operated by Transocean for BP exploded in 2010, causing the largest accidental oil spill in history.<em> Deepwater Horizon</em> exploded off the coast of Louisiana in, for the point, what large North American gulf?", "answer": "<b> Gulf of Mexico</b> (\u201dgulf of\u201d not needed after mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Carved prisms known as congs are found in ancient burial sites in this country, and are usually carved from jade. A colossal statue of a religious figure was carved into a cliffside at Leshan in this country. One emperor of this country had several thousand weapons, horses and soldiers with unique faces made for his tomb out of clay. For the point, name this country where Shi Huangdi commissioned the Terracotta warriors and the Forbidden Palace was built in Beijing.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b> (or<b> Zhongguo</b>) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After losing sight of the<em> Swan</em> during a storm, this man accused the captain Thomas Doughty of witchcraft and had him executed. On one raid, this man captured the Manila galleon<em> Cacafuego</em> and discovered California, christening the land \u201cNova Albion.\u201d This man boasted of \u201csingeing the beard of the king of Spain\u201d after surprising the Spanish Armada at Cadiz. For the point, name this English captain of the<em> Golden Hind</em> who completed the second circumnavigation of the globe.", "answer": "Sir Francis<b> Drake</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}